<pmc-articleset>
  <article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.4">
    <!--The publisher of this article does not allow downloading of the full text in XML form.-->
    <front>
      <journal-meta>
        <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cancer</journal-id>
        <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cancer</journal-id>
        <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">319</journal-id>
        <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">nihpa</journal-id>
        <journal-title-group>
          <journal-title>Cancer</journal-title>
        </journal-title-group>
        <issn pub-type="ppub">0008-543X</issn>
        <issn pub-type="epub">1097-0142</issn>
        <custom-meta-group>
          <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>pmc-is-collection-domain</meta-name>
            <meta-value>yes</meta-value>
          </custom-meta>
          <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>pmc-collection-title</meta-name>
            <meta-value>NIHPA Author Manuscripts</meta-value>
          </custom-meta>
        </custom-meta-group>
      </journal-meta>
      <article-meta>
        <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6636637</article-id>
        <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC6636637.1</article-id>
        <article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">6636637</article-id>
        <article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">6636637</article-id>
        <article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id">NIHMS1039600</article-id>
        <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30427539</article-id>
        <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cncr.31850</article-id>
        <article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id-alternative">NIHMS1039600</article-id>
        <article-id pub-id-type="manuscript-id-alternative">NIHPA1039600</article-id>
        <article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version>
        <article-categories>
          <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
            <subject>Article</subject>
          </subj-group>
        </article-categories>
        <title-group>
          <article-title>Regional Differences in Gallbladder Cancer Pathogenesis: Insights From a Multi-Institutional Comparison of Tumor Mutations</article-title>
        </title-group>
        <contrib-group>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Narayan</surname>
              <given-names initials="RR">Raja R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <degrees>MD, MPH</degrees>
            <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
            <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Creasy</surname>
              <given-names initials="JM">John M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <degrees>MD</degrees>
            <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
            <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Goldman</surname>
              <given-names initials="DA">Debra A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <degrees>MS</degrees>
            <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Gönen</surname>
              <given-names initials="M">Mithat</given-names>
            </name>
            <degrees>PhD</degrees>
            <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Kandoth</surname>
              <given-names initials="C">Cyriac</given-names>
            </name>
            <degrees>PhD</degrees>
            <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Kundra</surname>
              <given-names initials="R">Ritika</given-names>
            </name>
            <degrees>MS</degrees>
            <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Solit</surname>
              <given-names initials="DB">David B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <degrees>MD</degrees>
            <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Askan</surname>
              <given-names initials="G">Gokce</given-names>
            </name>
            <degrees>MD</degrees>
            <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Klimstra</surname>
              <given-names initials="DS">David S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <degrees>MD</degrees>
            <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Basturk</surname>
              <given-names initials="O">Olca</given-names>
            </name>
            <degrees>MD</degrees>
            <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">6</xref>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Allen</surname>
              <given-names initials="PJ">Peter J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <degrees>MD</degrees>
            <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Balachandran</surname>
              <given-names initials="VP">Vinod P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <degrees>MD</degrees>
            <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>D’Angelica</surname>
              <given-names initials="MI">Michael I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <degrees>MD</degrees>
            <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>DeMatteo</surname>
              <given-names initials="RP">Ronald P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <degrees>MD</degrees>
            <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Drebin</surname>
              <given-names initials="JA">Jeffrey A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <degrees>MD</degrees>
            <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Kingham</surname>
              <given-names initials="TP">T. Peter</given-names>
            </name>
            <degrees>MD</degrees>
            <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Simpson</surname>
              <given-names initials="AL">Amber L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <degrees>PhD</degrees>
            <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Abou-Alfa</surname>
              <given-names initials="GK">Ghassan K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <degrees>MD</degrees>
            <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Harding</surname>
              <given-names initials="JJ">James J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <degrees>MD</degrees>
            <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>O’Reilly</surname>
              <given-names initials="EM">Eileen M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <degrees>MD</degrees>
            <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">7</xref>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Butte</surname>
              <given-names initials="JM">Jean M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <degrees>MD</degrees>
            <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">8</xref>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Matsuyama</surname>
              <given-names initials="R">Ryusei</given-names>
            </name>
            <degrees>MD</degrees>
            <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A9">9</xref>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Endo</surname>
              <given-names initials="I">Itaru</given-names>
            </name>
            <degrees>MD</degrees>
            <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A9">9</xref>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name name-style="western">
              <surname>Jarnagin</surname>
              <given-names initials="WR">William R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <degrees>MD</degrees>
            <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
          </contrib>
        </contrib-group>
        <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Hepatopancreatobiliary Service, Department of Surgery, Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center, New York, New York</aff>
        <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Surgery, Stanford University School of Medicine, Stanford, California</aff>
        <aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Surgery, New York Presbyterian Hospital, Weill Cornell Medical Center, New York, New York</aff>
        <aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Department of Epidemiology and Biostatistics, Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center, New York, New York</aff>
        <aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Marie-Josee and Henry R. Kravis Center for Molecular Oncology, Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center, New York, New York</aff>
        <aff id="A6"><label>6</label>Department of Pathology, Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center, New York, New York</aff>
        <aff id="A7"><label>7</label>Gastrointestinal Oncology Service, Department of Medicine, Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center, New York, New York</aff>
        <aff id="A8"><label>8</label>Department of Gastrointestinal Surgery, Arturo, Lopez Perez Foundation Cancer Institute, Santiago, Chile</aff>
        <aff id="A9"><label>9</label>Department of Gastroenterological Surgery, Yokohama City University School of Medicine, Yokohama, Japan</aff>
        <author-notes>
          <fn fn-type="con" id="FN1">
            <p id="P1">AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS</p>
            <p id="P2"><bold>Raja R. Narayan:</bold> Conceptualization, data curation, formal analysis, investigation, methodology, project administration, resources, supervision, validation, visualization, writing–original draft, and writing–review and editing. <bold>John M. Creasy:</bold> Conceptualization, data curation, formal analysis, investigation, methodology, project administration, resources, and writing–review and editing. <bold>Debra A. Goldman:</bold> Conceptualization, formal analysis, methodology, validation, visualization, writing–original draft, and writing–review and editing. <bold>Mithat Gönen:</bold> Conceptualization, formal analysis, methodology, validation, and writing–review and editing. <bold>Cyriac Kandoth:</bold> Conceptualization, formal analysis, methodology, validation, visualization, writing–original draft, and writing–review and editing. <bold>Ritika Kundra:</bold> Formal analysis, methodology, validation, visualization, and writing–review and editing. <bold>David B. Solit:</bold> Investigation, methodology, resources, supervision, validation, and writing–review and editing. <bold>Gokce Askan:</bold> Data curation, formal analysis, investigation, methodology, resources, validation, visualization, and writing–review and editing. <bold>David S. Klimstra:</bold> Data curation, formal analysis, investigation, validation, visualization, and writing–review and editing. <bold>Olca Basturk:</bold> Data curation, formal analysis, investigation, methodology, resources, validation, visualization, and writing–review and editing. <bold>Peter J. Allen:</bold> Data curation, investigation, methodology, resources, supervision, and writing–review and editing. <bold>Vinod P. Balachandran:</bold> Data curation, investigation, methodology, resources, supervision, and writing–review and editing. <bold>Michael I. D’Angelica:</bold> Data curation, investigation, methodology, resources, supervision, and writing–review and editing. <bold>Ronald P. DeMatteo:</bold> Data curation, investigation, methodology, resources, supervision, and writing–review and editing. <bold>Jeffrey A. Drebin:</bold> Investigation, methodology, resources, supervision, and writing–review and editing. <bold>T. Peter Kingham:</bold> Data curation, investigation, methodology, resources, supervision, and writing–review and editing. <bold>Amber L. Simpson:</bold> Investigation, methodology, resources, supervision, and writing–review and editing. <bold>Ghassan K. Abou-Alfa:</bold> Data curation, investigation, methodology, resources, supervision, and writing–review and editing. <bold>James J. Harding:</bold> Data curation, investigation, methodology, resources, supervision, and writing–review and editing. <bold>Eileen M. O’Reilly:</bold> Data curation, investigation, methodology, resources, supervision, and writing–review and editing. <bold>Jean M. Butte:</bold> Conceptualization, data curation, investigation, methodology, project administration, resources, supervision, and writing–review and editing. <bold>Ryusei Matsuyama:</bold> Conceptualization, data curation, investigation, methodology, project administration, resources, supervision, and writing–review and editing. <bold>Itaru Endo:</bold> Conceptualization, data curation, investigation, methodology, project administration, resources, supervision, and writing–review and editing. <bold>William R. Jarnagin:</bold> Conceptualization, data curation, formal analysis, investigation, methodology, project administration, resources, supervision, validation, and writing–review and editing.</p>
          </fn>
          <corresp id="CR1"><bold>Corresponding author:</bold> William R. Jarnagin, MD, Hepatopancreatobiliary Service, Department of Surgery, Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center, 1275 York Ave, Rm C-891, New York, NY 10065; <email>jarnagiw@mskcc.org</email></corresp>
          <fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN2">
            <p id="P36">CONFLICT OF INTEREST DISCLOSURES</p>
            <p id="P37">Ghassan Abou-Alfa has received grants from Acta Biologica, Agios, Array, AstraZeneca, Bayer, BeiGene, Bristol-Myers Squibb, Casi Pharmaceuticals, Celgene, Exelixis, Genentech, Halozyme, Incyte, Lilly, MabVax Therapeutics, Novartis, OncoQuest Inc, Polaris Puma, QED, and Roche, and has acted as a paid consultant for 3DMedcare, Agios, Alignmed, Amgen, Antengene, Aptus, Aslan, Astellas, AstraZeneca, Bayer, BeiGene, Bioline, Bristol-Myers Squibb, Boston Scientific, BridgeBio, CARsgen, Celgene, Casi Pharmaceuticals, Cipla, CytomX, Daiichi, Debio, Delcath, Eisai, Exelixis, Genoscience Pharma, Gilead, Halozyme, Hengrui Therapeutics, Inovio, Ipsen, Jazz, Jansen, Kyowa Kirin, LAM, Lilly, Loxo, Merck, Mina, NewLink Genetics, Novella, Onxeo, PCI Biotech, Pfizer, PharmaCyte Biotech Inc, Pharmacyclics, Pier is, QED, Redhill, Sanofi, Servier, Silenseed, Sillajen, Sobi, Targovax, Tekmira, twoXAR, Vicus, Yakult, and Yiviva for work performed outside of the current study.</p>
          </fn>
        </author-notes>
        <pub-date pub-type="epub">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2018</year>
        </pub-date>
        <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2019</year>
        </pub-date>
        <volume>125</volume>
        <issue>4</issue>
        <issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">338358</issue-id>
        <fpage>575</fpage>
        <lpage>585</lpage>
        <pub-history>
          <event event-type="nihms-submitted">
            <date>
              <day>06</day>
              <month>07</month>
              <year>2019</year>
            </date>
          </event>
          <event event-type="pmc-release">
            <date>
              <day>15</day>
              <month>02</month>
              <year>2020</year>
            </date>
          </event>
          <event event-type="pmc-live">
            <date>
              <day>15</day>
              <month>02</month>
              <year>2020</year>
            </date>
          </event>
          <event event-type="pmc-last-change">
            <date iso-8601-date="2024-06-16 02:25:18.673">
              <day>16</day>
              <month>06</month>
              <year>2024</year>
            </date>
          </event>
        </pub-history>
        <self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="nihms-1039600.pdf"/>
        <abstract id="ABS1">
          <sec id="S1">
            <title>BACKGROUND:</title>
            <p id="P3">Although rare in the United States, gallbladder cancer (GBCA) is a common cause of cancer death in some parts of the world. To investigate regional differences in pathogenesis and outcomes for GBCA, tumor mutations were analyzed from a sampling of specimens.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="S2">
            <title>METHODS:</title>
            <p id="P4">Primary tumors from patients with GBCA who were treated in Chile, Japan, and the United States between 1999 and 2016 underwent targeted sequencing of known cancer-associated genes. Fisher exact and Kruskal-Wallis tests assessed differences in clinicopathologic and genetic factors. Kaplan-Meier methods evaluated differences in overall survival from the time of surgery between mutations.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="S3">
            <title>RESULTS:</title>
            <p id="P5">A total of 81 patients were included. Japanese patients (11 patients) were older (median age, 72 years [range, 54–81 years]) compared with patients from Chile (21 patients; median age, 59 years [range, 32–73 years]) and the United States (49 patients; median age, 66 years [range, 46–87 years]) (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .002) and had more well-differentiated tumors (46% vs 0% for Chile/United States; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &lt; .001) and fewer gallstone-associated cancers (36% vs 67% for Chile and 69% for the United States; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .13). Japanese patients had a median mutation burden of 6 (range, 1–23) compared with Chile (median mutation burden, 7 [range, 3–20]) and the United States (median mutation burden, 4 [range, 0–27]) (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .006). Tumors from Japanese patients lacked AT-rich interaction domain 1A (<italic toggle="yes">ARID1A</italic>) and phosphatidylinositol-4,5-bisphosphate 3-kinase catalytic subunit alpha (<italic toggle="yes">PIK3CA</italic>) mutations, whereas Chilean tumors lacked Erb-B2 receptor tyrosine kinase 3 (<italic toggle="yes">ERBB3</italic>) and AT-rich interaction domain 2 (<italic toggle="yes">APID2</italic>) mutations. SMAD family member 4 (<italic toggle="yes">SMAD4</italic>) was found to be mutated similarly across centers (38% in Chile, 36% in Japan, and 27% in the United States; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .68) and was univariately associated with worse overall survival (median, 10 months vs 25 months; <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = .039). At least one potentially actionable gene was found to be altered in 80% of tumors.</p>
          </sec>
          <sec id="S4">
            <title>CONCLUSIONS:</title>
            <p id="P6">Differences in clinicopathologic variables suggest the possibility of distinct GBCA pathogenesis in Japanese patients, which may be supported by differences in mutation pattern. Among all centers, <italic toggle="yes">SMAD4</italic> mutations were detected in approximately one-third of patients and may represent a converging factor associated with worse survival. The majority of patients carried mutations in actionable gene targets, which may inform the design of future trials.</p>
          </sec>
        </abstract>
        <kwd-group>
          <kwd>cancer genes</kwd>
          <kwd>gallbladder neoplasm</kwd>
          <kwd>gene target</kwd>
          <kwd>precision medicine</kwd>
          <kwd>tumor mutation</kwd>
        </kwd-group>
        <custom-meta-group>
          <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name>
            <meta-value>0</meta-value>
          </custom-meta>
          <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name>
            <meta-value>yes</meta-value>
          </custom-meta>
          <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name>
            <meta-value>no</meta-value>
          </custom-meta>
          <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name>
            <meta-value>yes</meta-value>
          </custom-meta>
          <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name>
            <meta-value>no</meta-value>
          </custom-meta>
          <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name>
            <meta-value>no</meta-value>
          </custom-meta>
          <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name>
            <meta-value>yes</meta-value>
          </custom-meta>
          <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name>
            <meta-value>no</meta-value>
          </custom-meta>
          <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name>
            <meta-value>yes</meta-value>
          </custom-meta>
          <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name>
            <meta-value>no</meta-value>
          </custom-meta>
          <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name>
            <meta-value>no</meta-value>
          </custom-meta>
          <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name>
            <meta-value>no</meta-value>
          </custom-meta>
          <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name>
            <meta-value>no</meta-value>
          </custom-meta>
          <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name>
            <meta-value>no</meta-value>
          </custom-meta>
          <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name>
            <meta-value>no</meta-value>
          </custom-meta>
          <custom-meta>
            <meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name>
            <meta-value>yes</meta-value>
          </custom-meta>
        </custom-meta-group>
      </article-meta>
    </front>
  </article>
</pmc-articleset>
